<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A discourse concerning the affaires of Ireland.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1650</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 23 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 7 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A81510</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing D1583</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E619_7</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R206366</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99865527</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99865527</idno>
            <idno type="VID">117772</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A81510)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 117772)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 95:E619[7])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A discourse concerning the affaires of Ireland.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>12 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Giles Calvert,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1650.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Decemb: 10th 1650".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Ireland --  History --  17th century --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-11</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-11</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="discourse">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:117772:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>A DISCOURSE Concerning the AFFAIRES OF IRELAND.</head>
            <head type="sub">LONDON, Printed for <hi>Giles Calvert.</hi> 1650.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hey that go about to conquer <hi>Ireland,</hi> and to reduce it to a form of compliance and obedience, ſhall find inward advantages from the conſciences of their enemies, and deſignment of providence to purſue thoſe ſins in which they lye, ſtubborneſs, idleneſs, ingratitude, with thoſe puniſhments which are <hi>aſpectabiles,</hi> and not uſually adjourned to the general doom of the great day. A thing of the largeſt inhance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of enterpriſe and extent of poſſibilities, when <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vids</hi> Sword is drawn out of the ſheath of the <hi>Ephod,</hi> and we ſtand bound, not onely by the fundamental Max<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ims of State, but by the very tenour and right of our be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing (which as it is antecedent to State-relations, ſo it is primalily obliging) to be inſtruments in the hand of God, aſſuming us for the reſpective diſtributing and awarding his judgments.</p>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:117772:2"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Ireland</hi> hath been formerly to us what <hi>Italy</hi> was to the <hi>French,</hi> a grave or <hi>Caemetery,</hi> a burden to our State ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then a profit, and it almoſt ſtood like <hi>France</hi> in our Title, the ground uncertain; we have had a ſucceſſive right for hundreds of years, no particular diſpathy with the Nation, but what was accidental, and of a ſecondary intention from our different Religion, and thoſe reven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges which are deepeſt impreſſed, and have the moſt inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lible character (Religion towards their Country making it Sacramental) ſet on them amidſt the often ſtruglings for the life of their liberty; For <hi>Nimrods</hi> and hunters of men know this, that if the people, that unruly beaſt, be not kill'd at one blow, their diſtemperd bloud will be unfit to dye the Robes of Soveraignty. But if we look about the world, the Art of keeping that which the ſword bequeaths, and preſents no other Title but what howſoever the conquered thinks unjuſt, is almoſt among things loſt, in which the <hi>Romans</hi> were their Crafts-maſters: And 'tis in our hopes, that as ſome no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ſpirits have renewed their Diſcipline and inſtaured the ancient credit, and ſeverity of the field; ſo this conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable part of wiſdom ſhall not long lie neglected.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Spaniard</hi> ſeems to have ſome skill in this ſecret of Government, as the <hi>Italians</hi> ſay, where they fix their Empires they are eternal; but every one knows to well their Arts, as likewiſe the <hi>Turks.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But to come ſomewhat nearer the buſineſſe, ſince the wiſdom of the State hath looked on that unpoliſht part of their Dominion, and deſired wiſely to ſecure it, as the avenues and approaches of this Nation, and the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent caſe of things gives us opportunity, we may exerciſe that part of wiſdom which looks forwards.</p>
            <p>We are not generally now of ſo quick a ſence of out
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:117772:2"/>ſufferings, nor are the iſſues of our zeal ſo ſtrong, as to actuate our paſſions into a general extirpation of ſo large a moity of <hi>Chriſtendom,</hi> we are better taught, it is the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve of Omnipotency to puniſh with deluges; for as inſeriour Tribunals do not reach all ſins, ſo do they not take notice of all perſons in their collective capacities: How ſhall the corrective part of juſtice which is moſt allowable, have any room when it comes with fire to burn up its ſubject?</p>
            <p>Chriſtians by a more exalted advanced Diſcripline more accompliſhing its deſign, as the great medium of rational ſociety &amp; commiſſure of mankind, hath taught us other ſecurities then revenge, which always (if great &amp; politickly univerſal) ſwells over the banks &amp; bounds of Chriſtianity: or if limitted and confin'd leaving exaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perations in the perſons, gives an eternity and infinity to evil. We proceed not to the defalcation of a perſon who is not incurable, and to count any one deſperate and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>relict, is tacitely to reſolve not to live up to the exten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive latitude, and intenſive heigth of our Religion, whoſe exemplarity, if drawn out and approximated to perſons in the circumſtances of duties, would expel from ratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal nature, and diſpoſeſs any baſeneſs that pretends to render it inſanable.</p>
            <p>There may be room for a general pardon, Goſpel Cities of Refuge, an overture which, unleſs the ſpirits of the enemy be very high, (as they are not in thoſe Provinces at this time) and ſo it breeds contempt, may have an effect, as carrying a hand of ſuperiority over a party, and is infinitely remote, far from any thing of equality, or acknowledgment to that party we have already de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigned to mercy before a victory; And all Reaſon of State beſides reaſon of morality, and experience in our Nation
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:117772:3"/>hath found it advantagious to reduce things to the Sanctuary, by firſt poſting up Pardons and tearms of compoſure, which no endeavour of enemies or braveries of contempt can make ſo tranſient, but ſomewhat will be ſticking; For thoſe Protections which were former<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly given, and Leaſes of life now, upon the ſubmiſſions of perſons, are of a more uncertain tenure, of a more privat mercy and advantage to Officers, then of publick reputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to the clemency of the State; the difficulty of ſuing them being anxious, their limited tearms uſually expire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing together with their Loyalty. The Majeſty of the State, which is religiouſly to be maintain'd with the cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumvallations of Laws and Prerogatives, may wiſely ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure this Act of mercy from ſlightings, with publick re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentments of the depretiation of ſuch an overture, with convenient reſtrictions and exemptions of perſons, and particular advantages to greater ſubmiſſions, or ſignal merit and ſervice, all in the for malities of Law given out, as at the requeſt of the Provincials.</p>
            <p>The caſe of Religion is of a deeper diſquiſition, the Nobility of that Kingdom have made it a pretence through all the courſe of their rebellions, and the <hi>Iriſh</hi> Sea is not tempeſtuous, unleſs beat upon by the wind of ſuch ſeditious pretences; They ſpeak with ſome paſſion, that our tyranny was worſe then <hi>Pharaoh's,</hi> entituling their particular intereſt with the general concernment of Chriſtianity, defence of Faith and Law of God. That Speech of the <hi>Spaniard,</hi> that they were a peeple ſo barba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous that he did not think Chriſt dy'd for them, is to be thought to be the reſult of his deſpair and anger, freely breathed out before his confinement he was to undergo, for his diſſervice to that Maſter that knew how to uſe the pretentions of Religion, in a deſign once dearer to him
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:117772:3"/>then his life. This fewel to the fire of the rebellion, is not to be taken away by a perſecution of their Religion; for they are ſo inhumane and unlike men, that we are firſt to reconcile them to our nature, humanity, and their own reaſon, before we can put them in a capacity of the duties and propoſitions of our Religion; For we muſt not underſtand any thing by Religion in its objective property extenſive to Faith, but many partial objects of aſſent complicated together, which like pearls would be caſt to ſwine, when they are repreſented to faculties utterly uncapable of rational Propoſals: and as natural actions which do not <hi>communicare materiam</hi> with ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituals nor ends, are firſt exiſtent before they were privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged by God into means and relatives to our end and eternities: ſo we firſt exiſt as men, before we are fit for the ſuper-inductions &amp; after-ſanctions of Chriſtianity; Nor would this fierce proceeding have a better reaſon from the nature of Religion, which is of another judica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture and appeal, and to be brought into the ſoul by in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trinſical arguments. Tortures although they weaken the nerves of Religion, yet they ſtretch them larger and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtend them, the nature of Religion arming; for certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, 'tis a Religion creeps on the ground and doth not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late to God, (which yet all Religion does) which neither by the profeſt ſeverity of punitive duty &amp; documents of mortality, or expectations and prepoſſeſſions of future ſtate (arguments of ſtate ſpeaking home to the ſoul) each of which the worſt of Religions, and therefore the wiſeſt will moſt pretend, could fire the affections natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally of a violent and inflameable matter into ſome ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſes of extaſy amidſt torments, where it hath all the advantages of its improvement to an high aſcent, that the inſtances of death turning all hopes to future,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:117772:4"/>and making them almoſt preſent can furniſh with, which one blaze at the time of death carries ſo much of confirmation in it, to popular minds that have not Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion in the intellect, as it is too dangerous an argument to be publickly urg'd, when wiſer heads are almoſt ſtart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led in privat. I'le add this one thing, if once this obtains that the power of ſounding and interdicting co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>munities of ſociety, ſhall meerly hang from the differences in our overtures of Religion, we having left plain fact and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pact, are already run into a rule of morality, for civil conſtitutions and ſanctions of State, our Divines will be our Lawyers; and this rule of morality, being according to the goodneſs &amp; malice of acts which are of a dubious and obſcure diſceptation, of various apprehenſion and circumſtance, we run our ſelves into the toyls of confuſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and affront highly ſociable nature, by giving it under the power of a Law, which is not a proportionate means to bring us to the end deſign'd in its Creation.</p>
            <p>The violent proſecution of their Religion will but pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure a further alienation from us, for their lying in that Religion being of ſecret reaſon, &amp; only punible by God that knowes it, and under his notice and cognizance, wee have no reaſon to put outermoſt which will ſatisfy their exaſperated ſpirits in the juſtice of ſuch proceedings; yet whatſoever Toleration bee granted in this neceſſity of things, private, or in out-townes it muſt bee compoſed with infinite caution that it may not ſeeme to give <hi>jus verum</hi> but only impunity; for by experience wee know that thoſe Edicts of pacification in <hi>France</hi> which the wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of the Councel of <hi>Henry</hi> the fourth lookt on as the only remedy left for to heal the wounds of that Nation, made by two great Factions, bringing that State to an Engagement which was infinitely to the diſadvantage
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:117772:4"/>of ſuperiority by making it ſtoop to a leſſer relation, was cauſe of moſt of the enſuing wars, and beſides being (as all ſuch things are) full of limits and cautions, and like a ſtream of an unconſtant and doubtful channel now receding to this party, now to that, would breed e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven in the exacteſt performances eternal matter of confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion; thus ſhould we be alwayes conquering and yet ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver overcome, a thing dangerous to us who have alwayes an eſtate there to loſe, when we have not our forces there to ſuccour it.</p>
            <p>I wonder when ſome Kingdoms ſo eaſily take the vein of the Religion of their Conquerours, fitting the Crown of Soveraignty and Robes of Prieſthood to the ſame per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, according to firſt inſtitutions in their different ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacities, and yet the principles of this Nation have riſen when there was nothing to commend or ſcarcely to make the Religion tolerable, yet ſurely 'tis fit we think God had his ends in this action &amp; ſudden conqueſt, and hath deſign'd the care to us of eating it out by prohibitions, in publick Towns ſerting up men vehement in their affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, exemplary care to be had againſt the founding of <hi>Iriſh</hi> Seminaries, inſtituting and executing all the ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt politick Laws againſt any ſtrangers that ſhould ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce them, or incenſe them, giving them to underſtand univerſally, that we ſtand now on tearms of compoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on with <hi>Spain,</hi> from whence they were wont to fluſh their hopes, and animate rebellions, and that whilſt there be born an even hand over the reſpective Nations, in tearms of compact or uſury, or indifferent (upon their ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curities) preferments and promiſed immunities and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>emptions: yet there is to be a particular boſome open, and encouragement to any that embrace the reformed Religion, care to be that Churches may be repair'd, and
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:117772:5"/>that function that ſerves at the Altar, be ſecur'd from the diſreſpect or contempt of their enemies, either in perſons or ſervice, and in the chief Cities and Towns there may be other Schools beſides the Univerſity in <hi>Dublin,</hi> the Statutes of which may be renewed, and good ſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pends for Profeſſors, and encouragements, the deloga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of which buſineſs, is referr'd to ſuch men as need no particular inſtructions; Hither the youth and Gentry of the Nation being invited, they may learn at leaſt to hear well of the Proteſtant Religion, and there may be laid a fair ground for inſinuation, or at leaſt a moderateneſs in their opinions.</p>
            <p>And ſince the plague, and war, and juſtice, (and indeed the Commander in this war hath been but a judge iti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerant) have laid waſt the Land; care muſt be taken of po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulations and reinforcing the ſtock of the Creation; yet in this buſineſs, we muſt not look on our ſending Colo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies as letting out the diſtempered bloud of this Nation, or as an honored exile for men of moſt broken hopes and profligate ſpirits, nor yet muſt it be the ſeat to minds diſcontented with the preſent Government, leaſt that controverſie be added to all the other Propoſitions of rebellion; but they muſt be perſons of indifferent, honeſt, ineffective ſpirits, fit for thoſe employments which do not exerciſe the fingers but the arms, and that not onely from the nature of that waſted haraſſed Nation which wants theſe Arts to recover it; but out of the account of the danger of fellulary idle profeſſions, which leave men wind enough to make up into diſcourſes. We muſt not judge the advantages of Colonies by the vaſtnes and cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuit of the ground they overſpread, but by the ſtrength and union; the firſt in this numerouſneſs of the <hi>Iriſh</hi> Nation, is rather to be prevented then wiſhed; for be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:117772:5"/>the uncomfortableneſs of cohabitation with ſuch ill neighbours, and their envy, which will be conſequent to our out-witting them, and flouriſhing in their own Countrey, which uſually Plantations do, as being parts of a whole ſomewhere confederate with them &amp; careful of them, and having freſher hopes, and only a general curſe on the Land to ſtruggle with, not yet by particular defilements having made it more barren, 'tis to break the power of the Nation, and to diſpark the <hi>Engliſh-Pale</hi> by cutting it into many ſtreams.</p>
            <p>Wiſe-men once thought, that if not the equality and evenneſs of our juſtice and Government, yet the parity of our condition with the <hi>Iriſh,</hi> would have brought them to an uniformity in State, and greater compliances; yet we have found, this may be hudled up amongſt the many overſights in proſecution of the relative intereſt of that Nation. We all know that for all theſe forty years of Peace and Plenty, their Nobility reſpected in our Court, their Religion not much oppreſt, they were in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grafted into our familyes, filled every place but our Churches, and had we not bin to deal with acts of cruelty but with nature, could our blood have ſoftend this Ada<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mant we had bin ſecure, for by the intermixture of mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riages, and interlacing privat allegiances, we conveyed <hi>Engliſh</hi> bloud into their veins, ſomewhat degenerating into their rudeneſſes, and naturalizing their incivilities; yet in the laſt horrible Rebellion, a buſineſs of ſecret cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes and ſecreteſt contrivance, all kindreds, tenants, wives were deſign'd, not ſcarcely the greateſt courteſie through the extenſive body of the whole Nation, in all the variety of relation, could endear them, as to ſave the lives of any by revealing their complices: never had humanity task to recover ſuch minds. All the advantage their diſſemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:117772:6"/>had was this, that the ruine ſooner and more uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſally overflowed them: had the main body bin in the chiefeſt Towns and Cities, they had bin a general terror to the Provinces, ſtrength to the Nation, and could not poſſibly have preſented to us a ſpectacle of ſo much ſad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and reſentment, by exhibiting to us the greatneſs of what we did poſſeſs once by the ſpace that their ruins cover'd; It would be good that the undertakers in Plantations be bounded by plots, according to exact preſcriptions &amp; the ſecurer conveniences of the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey, which muſt be more ſeverely lookt into, becauſe men in ſuch undertakings, will prefer the covetouſneſs of their deſires before the ſecuring themſelves or the Nation.</p>
            <p>It will be neceſſary to raiſe a Tribunal of juſtice; In this there are two caſes; either it may be Marſhal, according to the Military condition of the Nation, which kind of Government, as it is neceſſary it ſhould be put into ſuch hands whoſe actions are commenced with zeal and ſeverity, becauſe it hath ſomething more in it of abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luteneſs then ordinary forms; ſo is <hi>animalis juſtitia</hi> a virid way of domination for an unſetled State, and for diffuſing greater terrour, guarding the majeſty and au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority of the Laws: The other proceſs is by Judges and thoſe relative ſubordinations, as Sheriffs, Bayliffs, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> as we have in the Counties of <hi>England,</hi> and to which that Nation hath been formerly uſed, and it hath this of endearment in it, that as it is of a more moderate and civil Robe, and being a long harangue and ſeries of orderly acts and ſolemn proceedings, and containing under it many appellatives that are expreſſes of ſubor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dination and courſe, it will be the moſt infallible, viſible and living argument of plenary poſſeſſion, power, and
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:117772:6"/>protection, that our Reaſon from any Topick can make out.</p>
            <p>The Nobility among them maintayn their Authority over them with cruelty, taxations, rites of their Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey, barbarouſneſs in their creations and inſtallments into the ſucceſſions of their predeceſſors, by Genealo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gies far fetcht and deduced without any light of Hiſtory through the dark Mazes of Antiquity, and other En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chantments, which carrying with them the cuſtom and reverence of their Religion, do exceedingly bolſter up their uſurpt pretenſions: This is a rank of a doubtful uſage in the condition of this State, where there are not particular perſons unleſſe by a civill command of Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, and generall reverence of the conquering Nation, in ſuch a ſucceſſive heigth of blood and great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; and of theſe they will bee apt to remember that they were once below them, and may be again, conquer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Nobility living moſt unwillingly under free States, where there is not a Court to entertain them; yet for all this, the <hi>Romans</hi> by the Majeſty of their Nation gave a Title, paramount to the bloud and honour of the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Princes of the world, by hallowing any perſon that was intruſted in their ſervice; I wiſh this had been better obſerved in this State hitherto; that courſe which ſome Kings of <hi>Scotland</hi> took towards the Nobility, in a caſe almoſt paralel may be conſidered; but to deſtroy their petry Dominion, the peeple may be taken under the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediate protection of the State, and what Land they hold of their Lords, may not be rented according to arbitrary uncertain aſſeſſments, but certain rents and ſums, as our Farmes in <hi>England.</hi> But thus by weakning the Nobility, the peeple might riſe, dangerous to a pee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple that would not thank us for being diſenſlaved, but
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:117772:7"/>think themſelves nearer a general Liberty. For as God firſt moving the parts of the Creation, infuſed a quantity of motion in every body, and collectively over all the world; which in the main body of things, is ſtill the ſame, not ſuffering any imbelliſhment in its main ſtock, though by particular communication one part now moves in the air, another lyes on the ground: ſo there is infuſed into Kingdoms and the world a main ſtock of ſpirit, motion, activity, which although now is in the Nobles, and then in the peeple, according to the variety of the conjunctions of cauſes and bandying of contin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gencies; yet in its diffuſive iſſue is ſtill maintain'd inva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riable, entire.</p>
            <p>It may bee wiſdom to maintain ſtill a difference of Coynes in both the Kingdomes, and that ours may not bee tranſported thither to the impoveriſhing the Nation and furniſhing the Rebells with money, when many occaſions bring it into their hands, which may fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther them in their rebellion by procuring things they want for them in other Countries. And for further convenience in this buſineſs there may bee offices of Exchange according to the diſtinct proportions in <hi>London, Cheſter, Briſtow, Cork, Waterford.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If I knew any vertue they had, I would have it encouraged, making it if particular to run through the whole object and habit, if reſtrai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned and provincial, to bee general and National; or by actuating it if it be but in the power of their nature.</p>
            <p>To conclude; Let us not deſpayre of them, but carrying our things with wiſdom, expect providence, which is to acts of wiſe and politick natures what concourſe is to natural powers; and tho Hell may ſeem to plead dereliction with our Maker, as to the tenure of that nation, yet wee ſhall preſume on God by interpreting his ſilence into aliena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, impoſing ſignifications upon eternal acts, which we do not do in our owne before conſtitutions; <hi>Nulla eſt preſcriptio contra Deum,</hi> becauſe of the infinite right hee hath to any thing that was once his owne; if hee does yet take no notice of them: no man that ſpeakes worthily of God dares imagine that as hee made them by his word, ſo hee muſt forfeit them by his ſilence.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
